So, today's דף daf is מז. mem zayin. We pick up at
the very bottom
of מו עמוד ב, mem vav amud bet,
אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, three lines from the bottom. And here we finally
start talking about the issue of סירכות, sirchos, of adhesions. So let's
take a look. אמר רבא הני
תרתי אוני דסריכן להדדי, Amar Rava Hanei tarti unai desrichan lehadadi, two
אוני, unai, אונות, onot, I guess whatever, which are like the lobes
of the lung. If you, again, I don't know if you have
a picture in front of you, but if you see, the lung
is like two major sacs on each side, and then there are
these small little lobes off that are connected to them, sort of
smaller little sacs that are connected. Those are called the אונות, onot,
and the major sac is called the אום ome or the אם,
aim, אום, ome, which is sort of like the אם aim is
the word in Hebrew for the, well mother obviously, but it means
also the womb. So here it means like the major sac. It's
actually interestingly
some of the, it's often ignored in some of these discussions and
raises a lot of interesting questions in the ראשונים Rishonim which we'll
talk about. Okay, but here we're talking about these small little sacs
off of the side. So if you have two of them that
are סריכן להדדי srichan lehadadi that are connected to one another by
some type of a film or membrane that grows, which is a
סירכא. sircha. Okay, and again, as I said, there's a major discussion
what the problem of סירכות sirchos are. The גמרא Gemara is not
always so explicit, although it, you know, there's a lot of evidence
that shows that it's a concern that there's a hole and that
this came to cover over the hole. And as we know from
earlier discussions about other types of holes, and as we're going to
say explicitly by the lung, if some type of a membrane comes
or skin comes to cover up a hole once it already forms,
that's not acceptable. The animal is still a טריפה treifah because we
assume that this covering will tear, etc. So the problem with סירכות
sirchos is that we, the presence of a סירכא sircha makes us
suspect or concerned that there was a hole and that the סירכא
sircha came to cover it up, and if a hole did exist,
then the animal's a טריפה. treifah. So let's say you have these
two אונות onot that are connected to one another with this type
of, with this סירכא. sircha. So he says the following: לית להו
בדיקה. Leisu lehu bdika. You cannot check them, meaning that even if
you tried to somehow check to see whether there is a hole
or not, that won't suffice, which is interesting, which suggests that there
are possible ways of checking in other places, which we will talk
about, which we'll talk about when we get to later issues about
the lung, is there a way to like blow it up and
see if air comes out, etc.? Okay.
So and therefore, let's take a look. And therefore, meaning and therefore
it's a טריפה. treifah. והני מילי, Vehani mili, meaning and therefore it's
a טריפה, treifah, ולא אמרן אלא שלא כסדרא. Velo amran ella shelo
kesidra. But that's only if the lobes are connected out of order,
meaning we're going to see in a minute that there are three
lobes on the right side and two lobes on the left side,
again if you have a, if you have some picture to look
at that would be very helpful. I don't know if one of
you can open up those picture books. There's also that very thick
book שיחת חולין Sichat Chullin that you might want to look at.
So that's only if they're out of order. So out of order
would really mean a lobe from the right at combining with a
lobe from the left, or on the right lobe number one combining
with lobe number three.
אבל כסדרא, Aval kesidra, but if they are connected in order, meaning
with some type of, you know, this סירכא, sircha, this membrane connects
one and two or two and three on the right side or
one and two on the left side, היינו רבותייהו. Hainu revuyseyhu. Then
that's the normal way that they grow.
And therefore what? So תוספות Tosfos says, has one possibility, then היינו
רבותייהו, Hainu revuyseyhu, which it actually sounds like in the גמרא, Gemara,
means that this membrane is not evidence of a hole. היינו רבותייהו
Hainu revuyseyhu just means that this membrane is just a natural thing
that happens in the animal and you shouldn't assume a hole.
But
רש"י Rashi says it means, and this is interesting, is that even
if there were a hole, because they're close to one another, then
the growing of the membrane combined with the pressing of the two
lobes together actually successfully closes up the hole and means that the
animal will not reopen. So if you remember we've had that issue
before, you know, like if something developed a hole, I think it
was with the gallbladder right near the liver or something like that,
that if it's directly, if there's another organ directly on top of
it, then that might do a successful job of closing up the
hole. So here, although the lobes would not by themselves... because they
move around a little bit and they're not tight, if there's a
membrane it does, which is important because, again, what this then means,
when we have the case before by the hole with the two
organs next to each other, again I'm sorry just forget which it
was, but there you could say that the animal never became a
טריפה treifa because where the hole formed it was immediately covered. Here,
we're not saying that here. We're saying it was first to have
been a טריפה, treifa, but then the סירכא sircha grew and the
membrane grew and the membrane, you know, smushed them together, pressed these
two things together. So then we are saying that actually an animal
could be a טריפה, treifa, but if it successfully heals in a
way that won't be reversed, then it stops being a טריפה treifa
and I raised that issue before. So it does so that's the
way רש"י Rashi reads this גמרא. Gemara. It did have a hole,
but because it's the natural sort of way that these lobes connect,
if they're connecting one and three, then they'll pull apart it won't
stay that way. If they're connecting one and two or two and
three, they'll stay together and therefore it will stop it will close
up the hole. So that's the way... Wait, wait, Michael, one second,
let me finish my point. So רש"י Rashi reads it that the
first case was a case about a hole but it wouldn't stay
that way and I don't know why it says לית ליה לבדיקה,
lays lei livdika, but again maybe because in the act of tearing
it apart it's, look, the hole it'll form the hole, it's not
exactly clear because there are discussions about checking later. And one and
three though one and two or two and three or one and
two on the other side means that it will successfully seal the
hole. תוספות Tosfos suggest, notice that the גמרא Gemara here didn't discuss
holes at all. So תוספות Tosfos suggests differently that no, when it's
one and three or if let's say it's left and right, then
the fact that they're connected by a סירכא sircha means that then
they might pull apart and since they're now connected and the act
of pulling them apart will create a hole. So that's interesting because
sometimes we do say that the potential or the likelihood that a
hole will be created makes it a טריפה treifa already now. But
when it's one and two or two and three or whatever, then
because they're naturally go together, then we're not concerned that they will
come apart and therefore we're not concerned a hole will be created.
So that's what תוספות Tosfos how תוספות Tosfos reads this, which by
the way fits better with the phrase of לית ליה לבדיקה, lays
lei livdika, because it means even if there's no hole now we
don't care. Since they were connected like, you know, in an unnatural
way, it would have led to a hole and that's enough to
already define it as a טריפה. treifa. So that's the way תוספות
Tosfos reads it, but תוספות Tosfos does admit that a lot of
other גמרות Gemaras indicate that the problem of a סירכא sircha is
not what will happen in the future, the problem of a סירכא
sircha is that it indicates that a hole is there already now.
Okay, you had a question Michael.
Wait, wait, wait, I'm sorry, so I missed what תוספות Tosfos is
saying. What's תוספות Tosfos saying, that if it's one and three then
what, then you do have to check it?
No, no, no, לית ליה לבדיקה, lays lei livdika, but the problem
is not that the סירכא sircha is covering a hole, the problem
is that the presence of the סירכא sircha will mean that these
two lobes which will naturally pull apart because they're, you know, far
apart from one another, when they pull apart and you've got a
סירכא sircha holding them together, the pulling apart will cause a ripping
and will cause a hole to form. So לית ליה לבדיקה lays
lei livdika means even if you were to check it, you could
not say, oh there's no hole it's not a טריפה, treifa, because
it's a טריפה treifa by virtue of the fact that these lobes
which are far apart are connected and therefore it's by virtue of
the fact that a hole will form.
Do you understand that? But let's say that it's כסדרן ksidran then
what do you do with the סירכא? sircha?
Oh, then it's not a problem because then even if then a
hole won't form because they'll stay together.
So it means so a hole won't form which means that you
check it and you know a hole won't form or you still
don't check it?
No, no, same point, you don't have to check it.
Okay. But so again what I'm saying is, you know, how do
we know when to apply this thing like when one organ is
on top of another it
covers it
up and in this case it's the curvature of every time it's
kind of connected to the way or else the rib is plugging
it up and no worry.
Well, we're not talking about the ribs yet. We will talk about
the ribs. And by the way, סירכות sirchos to the ribs are
very common and actually we do largely say that a סירכא sircha
of the lobes to the ribs is not an issue. So we
will see about that. There's still a good couple of דפים dappim
left.
But the general issue, you know, Michael, is that you're right is
that we don't, you know, we don't extrapolate too much in laws
of טריפות, treifas, and but I will actually talk in a second
about how how that how sometimes you have to extrapolate since things
aren't discussed in the גמרא Gemara and that usually leads to a
wide range of debates. So let me actually address that right now.
Because you do see that there's this huge תוספות. Tosfos. So part
of what this huge תוספות Tosfos is discussing is the issue I
just said, whether סירכא sircha is a concern that it's covering a
hole or concern that it will make a hole. But the other
part of this תוספות Tosfos huge תוספות Tosfos is addressing an issue
that רש"י Rashi raised, which is not in the גמרא, Gemara, which
is what happens if you have a סירכא sircha combining a lobe
to the actual the אונא ona to
the אומא. uma. The lobes, by the way, to the ribcage, which
is very, very common will be discussed later. Anyway, so this is
never discussed in the גמרא. Gemara. So what's the הלכה? halacha? So
רש"י Rashi says...
So what are you calling
this?
אומא? uma? אלף ויו מם. alef vav mem. It's sort of like
אם em which is used to mean a womb. Okay? It's a
מם mem rather than a נון. nun. So if you look at
רש״י Rashi at the very bottom of מ״ו עמוד ב׳, mem vav
amud bet, רש״י Rashi says like this. He says,
let me see where to point you to this רש״י. Rashi. Hold
on.
Okay, so it's really actually one, two, three, four, five, six, seven,
eight, nine, nine lines from the bottom. And it starts with the
word דהיא אצלה. dehi etzla. You see that? Nine lines on the
bottom? דהיא אצלה. dehi etzla. So this says what if the lobe
connects to the actual major womb itself and it's right nearby? Okay.
So רש״י Rashi says,
okay, so he says,
דהיא אצלה מעשה בא לידי. dehi etzla maaseh ba leyadi. So this
case occurred to me.
ושאלה את פי רבינו יעקב בר יקר, v'shaalti et pi Rabbeinu Yaakov
bar Yakar, which was his רבי. Rebbe. I asked my רבי. Rebbe.
I didn't know what the הלכה halacha was. Is that the כלי
יקר?
Kli Yakar? What? Is that the כלי יקר?
Kli Yakar? No, no, please, please. He's a late אחרון. acharon. Okay.
Anyway, so I asked, so I asked my רבי, Rebbe, והתירו לי
לאכול. v'hiteru li l'echol. He said it was not a טריפה. treifa.
It was okay. ויש אוסרין, v'yesh ossrin, and some say it's forbidden.
והוא אמר לי טעמא וטעמם. v'hu amar li taama v'taamam. He told
me the reason and their reason. And his reason and their reason.
האוסרין אומרים הרי נקב. ha'ossrin omrim harei nekev. They presumably there's a
hole. Yikes. So number one, we start with the fact of a
סירכא sircha tells us there was a hole. So you know that
there is a problem. So now you have to prove to me
that you solved the problem. He says,
ולא מצינו שהותר אלא באוני. v'lo matzinu she'hutar ela b'oni. So we
only know the גמרא Gemara permits by the case of the lobes.
So we know there was a hole because of the סירכא sircha
and if you can't prove that this is okay, it's
אסור. assur. אבל כהאי גוונא, aval kehai gavna, but when it comes
to the major lung, לא קאמר. lo ka'amar. That's, so that's the
reason that those that say it was forbidden.
וטעמא דאוני משום שעומדים במצר החזה ומחמת v'taama d'oni mishum she'omdim bemetzar
hachazeh umachamat blah blah blah. Okay.
So I'm skipping this a little.
Okay.
One minute. I'm sorry. Now I'm looking for his reason. Oh,
וטעמא דידי. v'taama didi. It's the end of the line after it
says parenthesis מ״ח עמוד א׳ mem chet amud alef in parenthesis. And
the reason of my master is לא מצינו אומא בגמרא. lo matzinu
uma b'Gemara. The גמרא Gemara never discusses the major lung. ורבא Rava
לא אמר טעמא משום חום, lo amar taama mishum chom, which is
the reason the others said, I was just skipping that.
דבכל הריאה איכא. d'bechol hareiah ika. ורבא Rava פירש טעמא משום דהיינו
רבייתיה. peireish taama mishum d'hainu reviteih. So the
גמרא Gemara doesn't discuss the major lung, and the reason given is
when they are grown naturally side-by-side it's okay. כלומר כך הן גדילות
זו עם זו ואין נפרקות זו מזו. klomar kach hen gedilot zu
im zu v'ein nifrakot zu mizu. He emphasizes that they grow next
to each other and therefore they don't naturally separate. הלכך לא שנא
אוני ולא שנא אומא. hilkach lo shna oni v'lo shna uma. It
therefore doesn't matter if it's the lobe or if it's the major
lung. So here you have a great example by the
way that yes there are cases that are not discussed in the
גמרא Gemara and people did have to extrapolate. But that often led
to clear two separate camps because so many of the reasons, first
of all, it's so often so unclear the very reason of the
גמרא Gemara itself, right? Is this גמרא Gemara talking about covering a
hole or making a hole? You know, and the other reason that
was thrown in which I sort of jumped over was is the
fact that it's the inside the heat of the body, how much
does that affect it, what other things might be going on. So
how do we apply this to cases not in the גמרא Gemara
almost always leads to a מחלוקת. machloket. So here you have the
question about when it's connected to the lobe connected to the major
lung, is that just the same because they're next to each other
or no? Some reason that's different and therefore, and it's an interesting
sort of the implicit argument: if we know there's a hole, it's
the burden of proof is to prove that this is okay, not
that it's not okay. Now I wanted to, before continuing, I wanted
to also show you a very interesting thing in תוספות Tosafot because
רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam as we heard yesterday wrote a whole book
on טריפות treifot and sometimes he argues with his grandfather. And here,
not only does he argue with רש״י Rashi to say that this
is a טריפה, treifa, his language is quite strong considering that he's
arguing with his grandfather. So if you take a look at this
large תוספות Tosafot on the next page on מ״ז עמוד א׳, mem
zayin amud alef, the
long one that starts with the word יקר, Yakar, again the word
יקר Yakar according to his רבי, Rebbe, this רבינו יקר. Rabbeinu Yakar.
It's one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
either nine or ten lines down on the wide lines. Starts with
the word יקר Yakar on מ״ז עמוד א׳. mem zayin amud alef.
So he says the following. So רש״י Rashi asked, so he says,
יקר, Yakar, he's quoting רש״י, Rashi, והתירו לי לאכול. v'hiteru li l'echol.
פירש את טעמו וטעם האוסרין ונראה לו דשרי. peireish et taamo v'taam
ha'ossrin v'nireh lo d'shari. That's a paraphrase of רש״י. Rashi. That when
it's connected to the major lung with a סירכא sircha it's okay.
And then he says for רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam פסק לאיסור, pasak
l'issur,
רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam said it's forbidden, ואומר דכל המאכיל אונא סרוכא
באומא, v'omer d'chol hamachil ona s'rucha b'uma, anybody that feeds the meat
from a cow that the lobe was connected to the lung
itself, מאכיל טרפות בישראל maachil trefot b'Yisrael is feeding טרפה tref meat
to the Jewish people. Okay and then he speaks about why it's
forbidden. Okay. So it's quite a strong language. I mean obviously he
felt very passionately that this was forbidden but it's also quite a
strong language considering his father's own position, his grandfather's own position here.
So this is a great example that yes, Michael you're absolutely right,
there's a lot of things that are not in the גמרא, Gemara,
can we apply the principles or not, most often
what the principles are is not clear and the exact parameters of
the principle is not clear. Okay so that's the issue here about
a סירכא sircha and the question again is number one is it
a concern about creating a hole or it assumes there is a
hole which is generally what's assumed as you saw in the רש"י
Rashi as well,
that it's evidence of a hole and then the question is can
the סירכא sircha correct it. And here we're being told it can
only correct it when it combines two of these lobes that are
right next to one another. All right so if there's no questions
we're going to go on.
All right so let's take a look now back to the גמרא
Gemara in מ"ז עמוד א'. mem zayin amud aleph. Okay ואמר רבא
v'amar Rava top of מ"ז עמוד א', mem zayin amud aleph, so
רבא Rava also said, הני תרתי בועי דסמיכי להדדי hani tarti boei
d'smichi l'hadadi if you have two types of like, you know, right
like blisters that are next to one another. And again it's very
fascinating that how much is not stated in the גמרא. Gemara. The
assumption is as רש"י Rashi says but not stated in the גמרא
Gemara that the presence of two blisters would indicate that why did
these blisters grow up, you know sort of form, presumably there was
some irritation so it would be an indication of the presence of
a hole. One blister maybe not but two blisters yes, is an
indication of the presence of a hole. So if they're right next
to one another, and of course the question is how close means
close. תוספות Tosafot says anything more than one hair's breadth away would
be considered distant. So if they're two hair's breadths away it's not
close but if they are close then it's considered to be evidence
of the presence of a hole. לית להו בדיקותא leis lehu bdikusa
you cannot check them. Again it's a funny way, why doesn't he
just say it's a טרפה, trefa, but there are some cases before
if you remember where there were ways of checking, right about blowing
it up and seeing if the air forms, etc. Why do these
things not have a בדיקה? bdika? Because the whole point here is
is that the blisters or before the, you know the סירכא sirchas
covered up the hole. So if you test to see is air
escaping or not escaping what does that prove, you know, we say
there was a hole and now it's covered up either with the
סירכא sircha or the blister. So his point is we assume there's
a hole, this is not fixing the problem, the only thing that
fixed the problem was the two אונות onas next to one another.
So therefore because we assume a hole it's a טרפה. trefa. So
and no checking will help.
Okay now again notice this entire גמרא Gemara and the גמרא Gemara
before did not mention the idea of a hole once. All it
spoke about was blisters and סירכא sirchas and so on. However the
issue about בדיקותא, bdikusa, you know and we did say before and
we're going to say later about this way of checking about putting
it in water and water bubbles etc., that does allude to the
possibility that we are talking about holes and that is generally understood
what the problem is here. Okay so there we have the blister
issue and we have the bigger issue, the issue of the סירכא
sirchas or the adhesions. Okay ואמר רבא v'amar Rava now רבא Rava
also says, now we're going to spell out this issue about
the anatomy. ה' אוני אית ליה לריאה. hei uni it lei l'rei-a.
So there are five lobes to the lung. ארבע כלפי גברא. arba
klapei gavra. So now assuming the face of the animal is facing
the person. Now we do not mean when the animal is alive.
רש"י Rashi says we mean when it's suspended by its legs, which
is what they do after they would slaughter an animal, they suspend
it by its legs and the face of it would face, you
know, the butcher. Now if you think about that, I'll let you
do a mental picture of that. That means that what normally if
you're facing somebody your left is the other person's right. But if
the animal's suspended by its legs then your left is the animal's
left because it's suspended by its legs and it's facing you. So
if you just sort of envision this, your left is the animal's
left. Okay. So anyway, so now what do you have?
So you have the following.
So תלתא מן ימינא ותרתי משמאלא, tleta min yamina vetartey mishmala, three
lobes on the right of the lobe of the liver and two
are on the left. I mean on the right, excuse me, liver,
three lobes on the right of the lung and two lobes on
the left of the lung. חסר או יתיר, chasar o yatir,
if one lobe is missing or even one lobe is extra, או
חליף, o chalif,
or it's swapped, three is on the left and two is on
the right, טריפה, treifa, then it's a טריפה. treifa. Now this question
about extra is extra problem is an issue in general. There's a
גמרא Gemara later that speaks about כל יתר כחסר דמי, kol yeter
kechasar dami, I mentioned this to you before, an extra limb is
considered a missing limb, so if having a missing limb in that
place would make it a טריפה, treifa, having an extra limb makes
it a טריפה. treifa. That was a source of a lot of
bewilderment in the time of the ראשונים Rishonim because all of the
evidence was against that that was really a problem. So here interestingly
when we're talking about an extra part of an organ, although רבא
Rava says it is a problem because presumably of this logic, the
גמרא Gemara is going to say that it is or it's going
to immediately reject it. Now I should also say by the way,
you know, again this is an issue that I'm constantly going back
to, the fact that it says that if the numbers are swapped,
it's two on the right and three on the left, that's a
טריפה. treifa. Like, well why? I mean is there anything that is
injured, that is cut? You know if you say if it's extra
it's like one is missing, so then at least virtually it's like
one is missing. But why when it's swapped? Unless again you say
no even if it's swapped it means that one is missing from
the right side, so that is enough to be considered like some
type of a physical change that makes it a טריפה. treifa. Okay,
so that's what רבא Rava says.
So, any questions? Yeah. So I'm trying to understand, especially according to
those who say טריפה אינה חיה. treifa eina chaya. So this animal
is three years old. Yeah. And has an extra lobe, right? Does
it mean according to this that it must have grown it within
the past year and then it's going to die?
Yeah, you basically would have to say that, or you know you'd
just have to say like we often say, which is okay, even
when the evidence proves otherwise, we don't change the laws. Now one
way the רשב״א Rashba recognizes it's possible to deal with that, although
he rejects this answer, is that the principle of טריפה אינה חיה
treifa eina chaya means in the large majority of cases, not that
there would never be a case where it would חיה. chaya. Now
that would solve our problems so much because then we wouldn't have
to ask, oh what if you find out otherwise? It wouldn't solve
all our problems because we could still say that now we know
that these things are not a problem at all, but at least
it would solve a lot of our problems. But the רשב״א Rashba
based on the גמרא Gemara rejects that and says that whatever, I
forget the exact evidence, we haven't seen the case yet, but he
says it seems pretty clear from the גמרא Gemara that אינה חיה
eina chaya means no animal will live with it. So yeah Michael
you keep on going back to it, which is very legitimate, which
is that this is why הלכות טריפות Hilchos Treifos were a major
source of the issue of הלכה halacha and science because we constantly
ran into problems. And as you yourself said, not just what scientists
say, but sometimes what we directly observe. So yes it definitely is
an issue.
So I had one back to the question.
Yes.
Hold the phone closer, Shiki, I can't hear you.
Closer.
Is it possible that there are to say that there are different
kinds of טריפות, treifos, there's a טריפה treifa that as the Rabbis
said so far that it's not viable and there's a טריפה treifa
that's like an extra limb kind of thing where because of its
unusual
structure it's like I'm inventing a new category but
does that exist anywhere?
I suppose you could say that, you know, a sort of blending
of חיה chaya and אינה חיה, eina chaya, which you know you
assume anyway that the position that says טריפה חיה treifa chaya does
not say that like these are never problems, presumably that position also
holds that like a large number of these things does mean that
the animal will die. It just means that it won't necessarily die,
I don't know. So it is possible, or maybe to say what
you're saying a little more specifically, not in general that there's a
blending, but some of these extensions which are like based on principles
called, you know, כל יתר כחסר דמי, kol yeter kechasar dami, or
based on principles like you know when it's actually something is, you
know, exactly the organ is formed in a weird way, you know,
that those are different than types of טריפות treifos which are about
holes and injuries. So again that's an interesting possibility. As far as
I know the ראשונים Rishonim did not say that because the ראשונים
Rishonim were challenged by some of these new categories, how, you know,
what if we see that the animal does live? And as far
as I know they did not sort of suggest what you did,
but you're right, in theory you could say there's the base number
of טריפות treifos which are about the animal not living and then
there's sort of ways the גמרא Gemara extends them by talking about
like if the organ is formed in this weird way or if
things... which are extra, etcetera, which are you know maybe somewhat don't
have to pass the test of חי chai or אינה חיה. eina
chaya. Could be.
I'm just going to add one more thing.
Right. Right. Although it doesn't have to be a cow, it just
has to be כשר. kosher. But okay. All right, so let's see
where the גמרא Gemara continues with this. All right, so now we're
going to have a story about this question about the extra lobe.
So יוסף בר אחא... Yosef bar Akha... I'm sorry, I skipped the
line. ההוא יותרתא דאתאי לקמיה דמריימר. Hahu yoseirta d'asai l'kamei d'Mareimar. So
there was a case
with an extra lobe, it was brought to מריימר Mareimar to rule
on it. הוי יתיב רב אחא בבבא. Havi yasiv Rav Acha b'vava.
So רב אחא Rav Acha was sitting on the like on the
step, you know, on the front porch of מריימר's Mareimar home, and
presumably he knew what this person was asking him. So he knew
somebody was going in to ask a שאלה, shaila, he said, oh,
what שאלה shaila do you have? So he told him. So on
this guy's way out, he wanted to find out how he ruled.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, so רב אחא Rav Acha said to
him, מאי אמר לך? mai amar lach? What did מריימר Mareimar say
to you? So אמר ליה, amar lei, אכשורי אחשרא ניהלי. achshurei achshara
nihalei. He he told me that it was כשר. kosher. He was
not bothered by the extra lobe.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, הדר עול לקמיה. hadar ul l'kamei. Go
back and ask him again. No, there was some mistake, you maybe
didn't understand him correctly. I think you need to ask him again.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, so then so then when he was
asked again, מריימר Mareimar told this butcher who was asking the question,
זיל אימא ליה למאן דיתיב בבבא. zil eima lei l'man d'yasiv b'vava.
Go tell that person sitting on the on the front porch, on
the door, by the door, לאו כהלכתא כוותיה דרבא. lav k'hilchasa k'vosei
d'Rava. I know what I'm doing, okay? I don't the ruling is
not like רבא, Rava, an extra lobe is not a problem, בטרפא,
b'tarpa, regarding an extra lobe. So actually, this is quite cute and
there are other stories like this that we'll see in חולין Chullin
about somebody sitting sitting on the doorstep and sending people back because
he wouldn't he didn't believe that the answer was what they really
got and he didn't accept the answer. Okay, so this is an
interesting little trope here. But anyway he says, no, sorry, we do
I know what I'm doing and an extra lobe is not a
problem.
Now I'm just trying to make a rhyme here.
Oh, בבבא b'vava and בטרפא. b'tarpa. That's cute. Could be. Could be
at least the גמרא Gemara was trying to when the גמרא Gemara
rewrote it. Okay, maybe. Okay. והני מילי דקיימא בדרא דאוני. V'hani mili
d'kayma b'dara d'onei. Now
when is it true that an extra lobe is not a problem?
When it is in the row of lobes. So again, there are
three on the right and two on the left, but they're all
like in a row, you know, they're all on one plane. So
that's if the extra lobe appears within that row, בדרא דאוני. b'dara
d'onei. אבל ביני ביני טרפה. Aval beini beini treifa.
But if it's between them, it's טרפה. treifa. Now what does between
them mean?
Growing on top, between the bottom, or whatever there is.
No no no no no. Well, yes, but not even that. You
have your three where they belong and your two where they belong.
Now where's the extra one? So if the extra one is let's
say below the row of the three or above the row, or
let's say it's on the actual like in a you know in
a totally weird place, it's growing like straight from the middle of
the major lung, or if you imagine three and two and it's
like, you know, it's like, you know, if you imagine three and
two like on a flat piece of paper, you know, two on
the left side and three on the right side, and this would
be, you know, ביני ביני, beini beini, between the two of them
at the bottom. Something like that. So anyway, if it's not if
it's not just creating an extra one within a row, that is
a problem. But now the גמרא Gemara even within that will distinguish.
Let's take a look.
Okay. ההוא ביני ביני דאתאי לקמיה דרב אשי. Hahu beini beini d'asai
l'kamei d'Rav Ashi. So now one of these cases came to רב
אשי. Rav Ashi. By the way, it was occurring to me as
I was thinking about this the other day, I mentioned that you
have so many cases of practical פסק psak by טרפות treifos that
you get you know much much more than in any other area.
And it occurred to me that the reason in the גמרא, Gemara,
probably in real life, and it occurs to me the reason is
because in all other areas of הלכה halachic life, you control your
environment, you know? So if you're being careful and punctilious, right, you're
not going to have too many שאלות. shailos. I mean, if you'll
have a שאלה, shaila, it's because of it's a rare occurrence, it's
something, oh, I wanted to know if it was okay for me
to do this on שבת, Shabbos, something I never asked before, and
then once you ask it, you know the answer. Whereas in the
case of טרפה, treifa, right, you're not controlling it, you know, these
sort of these cases occur within the animals and it has nothing
to do with the amount of care that you're taking, so you're
going to get a lot of שאלות shailos that you have to
ask the rabbi because whatever the animal happens to look like, you
have to ask, and even if you know in theory what the
הלכה halacha is, you have to apply it to the weird, you
know, anatomy of the animal. So it just occurred to me that
that's probably why we have so many of these practical cases that
come up in the גמרא. Gemara. So let's take a look. So
there was a case of this ביני ביני beini beini that דאתאי
לקמיה דרב אשי, d'asai l'kamei d'Rav Ashi, it was brought to רב
אשי. Rav Ashi. סבר רב אשי למטרפה. Savar Rav Ashi l'mitrefah. רב
אשי Rav Ashi thought he was going to make it a טרפה
treifa because that's basically what we just taught, that an extra lobe
growing not in the row is a problem. אמר ליה רב הונא
בר מר אויא. Amar lei Rav Huna bar Mar Avia. So רב
הונא Rav Huna said to him, כהני חיווי ברייתא הכי אית להו.
K'hanei chivei baraysa hachi is lehu. All these wild snakes have them.
all of these wild animals, all the animals that grow that are
out in the field have these extra lobes.
וקרו ליה v'karu lei טפחי ונינוסא דורדא tufchei v'ninusa d'varda and the
butchers call it a little red boat. The what? A little red
boat, B-O-A-T. Presumably it was red and it was little, so therefore
like it's a common occurrence and they even have a name for
it and it's not a problem. Okay, now the question then comes
is,
so a couple of things. First of all, רש"י Rashi assumes that
by calling it a little red boat, somehow you imagine like a
little, like, you know, boat that trails behind like the big ships,
that this is only when it comes like between the three and
the two down at the bottom of the lung. But if it
comes like underneath the row of the three or underneath the row
of the two, that would not be normal and that would not
be included. The other thing is, let's say it wasn't little, let's
say it was big, let's say it wasn't one, let's say it
was two. So רש"י Rashi basically says that those things are not
normal. The only reason we're accepting this is because of the argument
that that's a normal thing, so if it's a normal thing how
can you call it a טרפה? treifa? If it's a normal thing,
it's just a normal variation. But those other types of things, if
there were like two of them or whatever, then that would be
a טרפה. treifa. Although it's interesting, he once again quotes that there's
a whole debate of the גאונים Geonim etc. about what is the
story if there's an extra one. There's also a question about let's
say an animal is missing one of the normal lobes, let's say
it has only two on the right side, but then it's got
this extra lobe. But this extra lobe is growing, you know, here
let's say, not in the row but like in the below them
or whatever where we had just said. So can you not only
say that it's not a טרפה, treifa, which is what we said
here, but can you actually have this count, you know, towards the
three lobes? To say that it's not missing a lobe. So רש"י
Rashi also basically rejects that as well, but that as well is
an issue of debate. So there's all of these debates, Michael, just
exactly along the lines of every possibility that the גמרא Gemara is
not talking about.
Correct, and they're saying effectively that potentially the anatomy of a wild
versus domesticated animal are different.
Well, I guess true, it depends on how you explain the word
ברייתא brayasa which means like, I sort of said wild animals but
that's not even necessarily the translation of the word. It might just
mean like, you know, of the field. רש"י Rashi says רועות באפר,
ro'os ba'afar, you know, just means all, you know, all the animals
have this, maybe as opposed to ones that- I mean, it doesn't
mean wild, certainly not in terms of the species, you're right. Maybe
it means wild in terms of a little bit like less fully
domesticated. It's not clear. But you know, it doesn't seem like the
גמרא Gemara is putting that much weight. What is interesting, I should
say, is also the question about, and this gets to the question
once again about science, is what if, you know, if you look
at this רש"י, Rashi, the first wide line,
so he says like this, just one line- I'd say the second
line, middle of the long, of the wide line, he says: ומסבר
רש"י למטרפה umisvara Rashi l'mitreifa שמע מינה shema minah לאו אורחא lav
orcha ובהני דידן uv'hanei didan דאית ברובא דידן d'ish b'ruva didan
that the majority of them have this problem,
so he suggests, so then he wants to say, what happens if
you actually have a lung that's missing it? Like could we reverse
it? So if like the majority of our animals have this extra
lung- this lobe, would you say the missing of a lobe now
all of a sudden makes it a חסר? chaser? You know, so
again, how much does our reality shift continue to shift things? So
these are all the later questions that the ראשונים Rishonim get into,
you know, how much do we go by the גמרא's Gemara assessment,
how much do we go by what we see, etc. Okay, so
let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, so we have the red boat. דורדא. d'varda. והני מילי מגואי,
v'hani mili migavai, all of that is only when it appears underneath
like I was saying. You have three and two and you have
one between them and the lobe.
אבל, aval, now on the עמוד ב', amud beis, אבל אגבאי, aval
agabai, if it's on the- if it's on the actual face of
it, meaning if it's on the like, you know, the major lung
itself, not on the sides of the lungs where or on the
bottom of the lung where the lobes appear, but it's actually smack
there in the middle of the lung- of the lung on the
face of it,
אפילו כטרפא דאסא טרפה, afilu k'tarfa d'asa treifa, even if it's a
tiny little extra lobe like like the leaf of a of a
myrtle, you know, it's still a טרפה. treifa. Of a הדס. hadas.
So תוספות Tosafos says, and what if it's smaller than the leaf
of a הדס? hadas? Maybe it's not a טרפה. treifa. Okay, so
anyway, so this extra lobe is okay because it's common, but depending
on where it appears.
Okay, אמר רפרם, amar Rafram, האי ריאה דדמיא לאופתא טרפה. hai reia
d'damya l'ufta treifa. If a lung appears like, so now we're a
little bit done for the moment with these lobes and סירכות sirkhas
and corpuscles, etc. So now we're going to go back to general
condition of the lung. If the lung appears like אופתא, ufta, which
is basically like chopped wood, it's a טרפה. treifa. Now what does
that mean chopped wood? So איכא דאמרי ika d'amri it looks like
chopped wood, the face of the chopped wood is white, so the
lung has appeared has turned white. ואיכא דאמרי veikka deamri בגישתא, b'gishta,
the feel, okay, of it, which is hard. And now the גמרא
Gemara explains what this means. איכא דאמרי דנפיחא, ikka deamri deneficha, like
if it's like it's blown up and it appears somehow, I don't
know but how the word נפיחא neficha means white, but it means
somehow that it's like it's blown, it's like somehow, you know, a
little expanded and therefore has a white appearance to it. ואיכא דאמרי
דפחיזא, veikka deamri depachiza, which is that it's hard, okay, so again
that's the translation of appearance versus feel.
ואיכא דאמרי veikka deamri and now some have a certain explanation of
what it means that it's like chopped wood, דשעיע, deshia, that it's
totally smooth, there are no indentations, so these five lobes are basically
are one with the main lung. דלית
ביה חיתוכא דאוני, delais bei chituchei de'unei, that the cut of where
the lobes appear are not present, so basically the lobes are just
an extension of the main thing and there's no distinction differentiation between
them and the main thing. And all the ראשונים Rishonim say that
it doesn't have to be a large distinction, but there has to
be some type of an indentation, some type of a thing to
indicate to create these separate lobes. Okay, so these are different ways
in which we say that the lung is deformed and therefore a
טרפה. treifa.
Okay, אמר רבא, amar Rava, again a statement of רבא, Rava, you
will notice that רבא Rava is doing a lot of ruling in
these cases. אמר רבא, amar Rava, now we're going to go to
a question of coloration of the lobe, of lung. We discussed before
about some colors if you'll remember yesterday, here he's discussing colors again.
ככוחלא כשרה, kechuchla keshera, if it's it has a bluish look, it's
כשר. kosher. כדיותא
טרפה, kediyusa treifa, if it has the black look, the lung, it's
a טרפה. treifa. דאמר רבי חנינא, de'amar Rabbi Chanina, שחור אדום הוא
אלא שלקה. shachor adom hu ela shelaka. This is by a statement
about the blood of the נדה, Niddah, menstrual blood, it said only
if it's red is it a problem, but if it's black, that's
also a problem because we say black was red but it got,
you know, exposed to oxygen or whatever and turned black. So here
too we assume that it's red, red meaning blood, red meaning a
wound, so if there's black coloration we assume that means that there
was a wound and now it's turned black and therefore the presence
of a wound is enough to assume that it is a טרפה.
treifa. Interestingly again though, notice that this is not on the list
of our משנה. Mishna. Our משנה Mishna spoke about holes, now we're
speaking about colors, even if colors means wounds, it's not exactly the
hole case in the משנה. Mishna. All right, so now the גמרא
Gemara goes on with colors. ירוקא
כשרה, yaroka keshera, if it's green, כשרה, keshera, that's okay,
מדרבי נתן, miderabi Nasan, from a story about רבי נתן Rabbi Nasan
which we'll have in a minute. אדומה כשרה, aduma keshera, red, כשרה
keshera is also כשרה, kosher, מדרבי נתן, miderabi Nasan, a story of
רבי נתן. Rabbi Nasan. Now you're going to say, didn't we just
say that black was a problem because it was a type of
red? So how could you tell me that red is a problem?
It's okay.
Isn't it supposed to be red? I mean, that's the color of
a lung.
Yeah, yeah, red here means not just that, means sort of like
like a red that indicates a type of a wound, like we
had this yesterday. It means that there's some type of a breaking
of the blood vessels from underneath. So there's the reddishness that you
get like when a wound is formed, you know, like a black
and blue type of a look. That's what this red means. But
yes, not the natural red, of course. The other question is that
didn't we say a minute ago that black was a problem because
it was a type of red? How can we say red is
okay? And the basic difference is that we're going to say that
just red, and like just green, as we'll see in a minute
or yellow, actually, question how you translate ירוקא, yaroka, let's say it
means yellow, that those things are going to heal, whereas once it
turns are a problem but they eventually will heal. Whereas once it
turned black, that's a wound that will not heal and therefore it
is it remains a problem. So let's take a look at these
two stories that are supposed to prove that these colors are okay.
So let's take a look. Okay,
actually, I'm sorry, I think that this ירוקא yaroka does mean green.
We're going to discuss in a minute greens and yellows. So let's
take a look. דתניא, detanya, here's the רבי נתן Rabbi Nasan stories.
דתניא, detanya, רבי נתן אומר, Rabbi Nasan omer, רבי נתן Rabbi Nasan
says, פעם אחת הלכתי לכרכי הים, pa'am achas halachti lecherachei hayam, one
day I went to the, you know, the islands of the sea,
I went on a little vacation, a little trip. באתה אשה אחת
לפני, ba'asa isha achas lefanai, and a woman came to me, שמלה
בנה ראשון ומת שני ומת. shemalah benah rishon umes sheini umes. She
gave her son a ברית מילה bris milah first time and he
died, second time and he died as a result of the ברית
מילה. bris milah. This is probably an issue of hemophilia, although the
story does not make it sound that way, because if it were
hemophilia you would be stuck with the problem for life and by
the way that is the הלכה. halacha. If there's evidence of hemophilia
then you do not do a ברית מילה. bris milah. And רש"י
Rashi interestingly right here points out because even though ברית מילה bris
milah is of course so such an important מצוה, mitzvah, you don't
give up your life for any מצוה mitzvah no matter how important
unless it's the big three. Okay, so anyway, her two sons died,
she didn't realize that this was going to be a problem.
שלישי הביאתו לפני, shelishi hevi'asu lefanai, the third son she brought to
me and said what should I do, should I do a ברית
מילה? bris milah? So ראיתי שהיה אדום, ra'isi shehayah adom, I saw
that he was red. אמרתי לה אמרתי, amarti lah amarti, so I
said לה בתי, lah biti, my daughter, המתיני לו עד שיבלע דמו,
himtini lo ad sheyibala damo, wait for the blood to be absorbed,
presumably there's a lot of blood going on between the flesh and
the skin and therefore that's the way he read
it, and therefore he's in danger and a wound will cause him
to die, so wait for the blood to be absorbed.
So what did she do? המתינה לו, himtina lo, she waited for
his color to normalize,
ומלה אותו umala oto and then gave him the ברית מילה, bris
milah, וחיה vechaya and he lived. והיו קורין אותו נתן הבבלי על
שמי, vahayu korin oto Natan Habavli al shemi, and then they named
him after me, they called him Nathan the Babylonian. Okay, ושוב פעם
אחת veshuv pa'am achat הלכתי למדינת קפוטקיא, halachti limdinat Kaputkia, and another
time I went to a particular to the city of
Cappadocia—I think we know where that is but I forget what that
is, maybe somebody has an English that'll tell you? What?
What does it say?
Cappadocia in Asia Minor.
There you go, Cappadocia. Okay. באתה אשה לפני שמלה בנה ראשון ומת
שני ומת שלישי הביאתו לפני, ba'ata ishah lefanay shemela bnah rishon umet
sheni umet shlishi hevi'ato lefanay, same story, her first two sons died
from ברית מילה, bris milah, third son she brought to me because
I happened to be there. וראיתיו שהיה ירוק, vera'itiv shehayah yarok, I
saw that he was a little greenish. Now, yellow maybe makes more
sense because of jaundice, but we're going to see in a minute
that the גמרא Gemara is going to really emphasize the green. There's
a whole question about in the גמרא Gemara and in the ראשונים
Rishonim what these colors are, but okay, I saw that he was
a little greenish. הצצתי בו ולא היה בו דם ברית, hitzatzti bo
velo hayah bo dam bris, and I sort of like peered at
him, looked at him closely and saw that he didn't have the
enough blood. Now דם ברית dam bris is an interesting phrase; literally
means blood of circumcision, which suggests that there's an importance for there
to be blood when you circumcise. Actually, in the גמרא Gemara there
isn't; the גמרא Gemara emphasizes the importance of just removing the foreskin.
It does discuss הטפת דם ברית hatafat dam bris when somebody does
not have a foreskin and you do that as sort of like
a pseudo מילה milah ritual, but there's a whole question—our liturgy or
whatever we emphasize the importance, בדמייך חיי, bedamayich chayi, and the role
of blood in the ברית מילה. bris milah. It's important, really, you
know, comes to the forefront in a way later in later generations
in a way it doesn't in the גמרא. Gemara. But anyway, here
the issue is not whether you're successfully going to do the ברית
מילה; bris milah; here the issue is whether he's going to live
or not. So the use of the phrase דם ברית dam bris
is a little strange, but nevertheless his point was the opposite of
the red point. The red point was there was too much blood
going there, it hadn't been absorbed yet into the into the flesh.
Here there was not enough blood that had yet been flowing through
the body.
דלא ליהוי, dela lehevei,
he wouldn't heal—right, there's not enough blood and he's in danger and
the ברית מילה bris milah will cause him to die. That's how
he's reading the situation. So אמרתי לה amarti lah and I said
to her, בתי המתיני לו עד שיפול בו דמו, biti himtini lo
ad sheyipol bo damo, wait for his blood to get flowing into
him. So המתינה לו, himtina lo, she waited, ומלה אותו umala oto
and gave him ברית מילה, bris milah, וחיה, vechaya, he lived, והיו
קורין אותו נתן הבבלי על שמי—got vahayu korin oto Natan Habavli al
shemi another child named after me. Okay, so anyway, so how is
that relevant to us? Because it shows that in these conditions the
animal, number one, is true is that health is endangered, but it
also shows that with time it will heal. So it won't be
a טרפה treifa if the lung has these conditions because these conditions
will reverse themselves, whereas a just a black mark presumably indicates a
type of a wound that can no longer be reversed. And now
the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss, continue discussing questions of color.
So let's take a look. אמר רב כהנא, amar Rav Kahana, ככבדא
כשרה, kecheveda keshera, if the lung looks like the liver, has that
type of an appearance, that's okay, that's a normal or within a
normal range. כבשרא טרפה, kevisra treifa, if it looks like flesh, has
a pinkish appearance, then טרפה, treifa, then that's no good. וסימנך, vesimnach,
the way you remember it is ובשר בשדה טרפה, uvasar basadeh treifa,
and flesh is a טרפה. treifa. So if the lung looks like
a flesh, then it's a טרפה. treifa. Okay. אמר רב סמא בריה
דרבא, amar Rav Sama brei deRava, האי ריאה דדמיא
ככשותא—if hai reia dedamya kechashuta you have a lung that looks like
כשותא, chashuta, which I looked in English is, it's translated as כסכתא,
kasachta, I have no idea what that is, some type of a
food I think, some type of a grain or whatever, I don't
know, וכמוריקא vechimrika and like saffron, וכעין ביעתא uche'ein beita or like
an egg, presumably the yolk of an egg, טרפה. treifa. So there
you have a yellow color which is a טרפה. treifa. A saffron
is yellow—is that correct?
Saffron is reddish? It's yellow.
Saffron is yellow.
Okay,
so then do you know what
כשותא—saffron chashuta is red also?
Well, and an egg is white also, but here we're talking about
the yellow version of it. Okay, so if it's one of these
types of bright yellows, it's a
טרפה. treifa. אלא ירוקה כשרה היכי דמיא—what ela yeroka keshera heichi damya
type of ירוק yarok is
כשר? kosher? ככרתי, kecharti, like a leek. Now it's the גמרא—there's Gemara
a number of גמרא Gemaras also when it talks about colors of
an אתרוג esrog and so on, that seems to be that the
גמרא Gemara did not have different names for yellow and green. Yellow
and green, it seems to have like one color for the whole
yellow-green, you know, whatever spectrum.
So there's always a question here,
is this contrasting a bright yellow to a dull yellow, that the
dull yellow is okay? Or is it saying no, no, no, anything
that's yellow, that's the ירוק yarok which is the yellow end of
the spectrum is a טריפה, treifa, but anything that's green end of
this yellow-green spectrum that's כשרה. ksheira. That's what it sounds like because
for example the by אתרוג esrog one of
the in סוכה Sukkah the משנה Mishna where it speaks about the
פסולים psulim of an אתרוג esrog or the potential problems, it speaks
about an אתרוג esrog that's ירוק ככרסא. yarok kekharsi. ירוק ככרסא Yarok
kekharsi like a leek. So again, it presumably does not mean
yellow, that's a normal color for an אתרוג, esrog, presumably it means
green. So ככרסא kekharsi would mean, you know, a leek which is
green.
So here we're saying that like yellow the yellow end of ירוק
yarok is פסול, pasul, the green end of ירוק yarok is כשר
kasher is not a טריפה.
treifa. People don't have green אתרוגים? esrogim?
Well, it's discussed in the גמרא Gemara whether ירוק ככרסא yarok kekharsi
is a problem. It's not necessarily a problem. It's also a question
about how green: dark green, light green, etc. All these are questions.
Okay, so we'll worry about it when we learn סוכה. Sukkah. Yes.
I didn't get these names in תוספות. Tosafos. Oh, you think indigo
means indigo?
Well, and then he goes on to say it's like sky.
Yeah, that's true. I'm sorry.
Right, right, right, right. That's true. רש"י Rashi explicitly says it's the
color of grass. But yeah, I didn't know in תוספות Tosafos when
he's turning it to blue because, you know, because then he says
there's a גמרא Gemara that speaks about about ככרסא kekharsi looking close
to the color of תכלת. techeiles. But we also know that green
and blue are similar colors. So it's hard to know in תוספות
Tosafos as well, right, how far is he going into that green-blue
spectrum? Yeah, so I don't know. That's why it always gets very
confusing. The גמרא Gemara before said blue was okay, ככוחלא kekhuchla is
okay. So, you know, so I don't know. All right, anyway, oh
actually no, that wouldn't be a problem because here it's also saying
that green is okay. So right, so if he's saying green-blue, wait,
what did the גמרא Gemara say before about blue? Yeah, it said
blue was okay. So that's true. So here if it's green and
you're saying it's sort of the green-blue is okay, that's all within
the same that's all within the same spectrum. So that's true. תוספות
Tosafos tries to read this green as somewhere in the green-blue area.
Okay, so now let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay,
so אמר רבינא: Amar Ravina: אטום בריאה. atum bereiya. Let's say there's
an obstruction in the lung, inside the hollow of the lung, presumably.
So again a question: would this be some type of a thing
which would cause the, you know, be a serious problem in the
health of the animal? Again notice, it's not in the formal category
of hole, but now we're dealing with different problems. Okay, so מייתינא
סכינא וקרעינא ליה. mayitina sakina vekarina lei. We take a knife and
we cut it open. Interesting: before we took a thorn, here we
take a knife. We take a knife and we cut it open.
אי אית ביה מוגלא, ei it bei mugla, if it has pus,
then ודאי מחמת מוגלא הוא, vadai machmas mugla hu, so it formed
as a result of the pus, וכשרה, veksheira, and it's כשר. kosher.
Why? Presumably that means it's temporary and it would heal.
ואי לא, ve'ilo, and if it doesn't have pus, then מותבינן לה
גדפא או רוקא—this motvinan lah gadva o roka will be familiar, but
we're doing it for the opposite purpose here. We take a feather
or some or some spit. אם
מבצבצא כשרה, im mevatva ksheira, so before that showed it was a
hole and it's a problem, here it shows that the thing is
not fully hardened, similar to the pus idea, that there's some air
going through it or whatever, some holes in it, and therefore it
would not have been it would, you know, it would not have
been a serious health issue. Then it's כשר. kosher. ואי לא, ve'ilo,
but if no if it doesn't move at all, so therefore there's
presumably I don't know no air feeding into this this thing, it's
totally hard, then טריפה treifa then it is a problem. I don't
really get the full מציאות metzius once you've cut it open where's
the air coming from? I don't know. But anyway, if it's somewhat
that it's pus-filled or somewhat more airy then it's okay. Okay, now
the גמרא's Gemara going to repeat a גמרא Gemara that we saw
before so this will go quickly.
Okay,
אמר רב יוסף: Amar Rav Yosef: קרום שעלה מחמת מכה בריאה אינו
קרום. krum sheala machmas maka bereiya eino krum. This is basically what
we've been assuming for the last day and a half, which is
that if a some type of a skin, a membrane, comes to
cover up where there was a מכה, maka, which literally means a
wound, but here our emphasis is much more about a hole, so
if some type of membrane covers up a hole, that does not
help. It's still a טריפה treifa presumably because that will not remain.
Okay, so that is the so that whole problem about סירכא sirchas
is if there once was a hole, you've got a problem. Okay,
now, ואמר רב יוסף: ve'amar Rav Yosef: האי ריאה דאוושא, hai reiya
de'avsha, אי ידעינן היכא אוושא, ei yadinan heicha avsha, if you have
a lung that makes sound, that whistles sort of when you blow
it up, if you know where the sound is coming from, then
מנחינן עלה גדפא או גילא או רוקא, manchinan ala gadva o gila
o roka, you put either like a straw or a feather. or
a spittle
right where you heard the sound coming from. אם מבעבע טרפה, Im
meva'be'a treifah, if it sort of flutters, it's a טרפה treifah because
that means there's a hole through and through. ואי לא כשרה, V'ei
lo ksheirah, and if not it's okay. למה חזרנו על זה?
Lamah chazarnu al zeh?
Because here's where it originally appeared. We quoted it yesterday to prove
the point that the hole had to be through both. But this
was sort of the quote-unquote original location. In the middle of these
discussions, you know, it was when it was originally taught, it was
part of this tradition of discussions about color and discussions about קרום
שעלה מחמת מכה, krum she'alah meichamat makah, so on. But you're right,
it's a direct repetition. Okay, ואי לא, V'ei lo, and if you
don't, ולא ידעינן ליה, v'lo yadainan leh, so and if you don't
know where the sound comes from, מייתינן שיחושא דמיא, maytainan shichusha d'maya,
you take a container of water פשורי pshurei of lukewarm water ומותבינן
לה בגווה u'motavinan lah b'gavah and you put it in it. בחמימי
לא, B'chamimei lo, not in hot water, דחפתי, d'chafti, that it causes
holes to shrink, so it would be not a fair test. ובקרירי
לא, U'v'kriri lo, and not in cold water, דמטרשי, d'matarshi, it makes
the skin hard, it might cause it to crack where it normally
would not have had a hole. אלא דבדקינן לה
בפשורי, Ela d'vadkinan lah b'pshurei, lukewarm water. אם מבעבע טרפה, Im meva'be'a
treifah, if if it bubbles up then it's a טרפה, treifah, if
bubbles come out, ואי לא כשרה, v'ei lo ksheirah, and if not
it's כשרה. ksheirah. והא קא אוושא? V'ha ka avsha? And how come
it's making a sound? משום דתתאי אינקיב, Mishum d'tatai inkiv, because the
lower membrane has a hole in it, עילאי לא אינקיב, ilai lo
inkiv, but the upper membrane does not. והא דאוושא, V'ha d'avsha, and
the fact that it's making a sound, זיקא דביני ביני הוא, zika
d'veini beini hu, it's the wind that comes between the two membranes.
It went out of the inner one and got between the two
of them, but as long as it's not coming out of the
outer one you're okay. I mean it got out of the inner,
it's between the two, as long as it's not coming out of
the outer you're okay. One more thing. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi
Yochanan, ריאה שנשפכה כקיתון כשרה. reiyah she'nishp'chah k'kiton ksheirah.
Let's say the flesh of the membrane of the skin around the
lung has dissolved, so you still have the skin as it were
of the flesh of your organ, but the inner flesh is like
dissolved and is like liquid, like a pitcher. Okay, again I don't
know how that that could happen, but anyway it's כשרה. ksheirah. אלמא
קסבר חסרון מבפנים לא שמיה חסרון. Alma kasavar chisaron mibifnim lo sh'meih
chisaron.
So although it's lacking from inside, it's not totally filled with flesh
like it used to be, as long as it's not a hole
that went all the way through the wall, even though something got
removed from between the walls as it were or dissolved, it's still
not a problem. איתיביה, Eitivyei, the Gemara says let's I'll ask you
on this. רבי אבא לעולא: Rabbi Abba l'Ulla: הריאה שניקבה או שחסרה.
Hareiyah she'nikvah o she'chasrah. We say if a lung has a hole
or it's lacking. מאי חסרה? Mai chasrah? What does lacking mean? אילימא
מבחוץ, Ilima mibachutz, if it's something was removed and it went all
the way to the outside, היינו ניקבה, hainu nikvah, that's the same
as a hole. So how can you have lacking without it being
a hole? אלא לאו מבפנים, Ela lav mibifnim, it means something was
taken from the inside, but it didn't go all the way to
the outside. שמע מינה חסרון מבפנים שמיה חסרון. Shma minah chisaron mibifnim
sh'meih chisaron. You see that if something is lacking it's a problem,
even if it doesn't a hole. Like you can make a hole
in something without taking anything away, it just sort of pushes the
stuff to the side. So a hole has to go all the
way through. But if some of the flesh of the skin of
the lung is actually lacking, that's a problem even if it's only
on the inside, even if it doesn't go to the outside. לא
שמיה חסרון? Lo sh'meih chisaron? No. לעולם
מבחוץ, L'olam mibachutz, really on the outside
we're talking about that the hole went to the outside and חסרון
chisaron went to the outside. ודקאמרת היינו ניקבה, U'd'ka'amart hainu nikvah, isn't
that the same as a hole? לא צריכא אלא לרבי שמעון, Lo
tsricha ela l'Rabbi Shimon, דאמר עד שתינקב לבית הסימפונות. d'amar ad she'tinnakev
l'veit hasimponot. Rabbi Shimon says a hole is only a problem if
it goes actually to where like the branches of the trachea branch
off. Not every hole is a problem. הני מילי, Hanei milei, that's
true, ניקבה דלית בה חסרון, nikvah d'leit bah chisaron, when it's a
hole that does not take anything away. אבל ניקבה דאית בה חסרון,
Aval nikvah d'it bah chisaron, but if it's a hole that actually
stuff is taken away as a result, that actually something is some
of the flesh is removed, then אפילו רבי שמעון מודה, afilu Rabbi
Shimon modeh, even Rabbi Shimon would say any hole is a problem.
So here we're trying to say an actual קולא kula that if
some of the flesh is removed, and here the example of that
is that it's dissolved, as long as it did not create a
hole, you're actually going to be okay.
Do we have to end now or can I read another line?
What? Okay I'll read one more line.
Okay, רבי חנינא חלש, Rabbi Chanina chalash, Rabbi Chanina got sick, על
לגביה רבי נתן וכל גדולי הדור, ala legabeih Rabbi Natan v'chol gedolei
hador, so he had a little ביקור חולים bikur cholim call. So
of course what do you do to cheer somebody up on a
ביקור חולים bikur cholim call? You ask him שאלות. shailos. Or maybe
you want to ask him שאלות shailos because you're afraid he might
die and you want to get his final teachings about certain things.
אייתו קמיה ריאה, Aitu kameih reiyah, they brought him a lung שנשפכה
כקיתון, she'nishp'chah k'kiton, that again the flesh of it, it still had
some of the outer shell but somehow some of the flesh had
liquefied, ואכשרה, v'achshrah, and he said it was kosher. Again I don't
know exactly what this מציאות metzi'us is. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, והוא
דקיימי סימפונות, v'hu d'kayami simponot, that's only true if the actual branches
of the trachea are still around, but if they have also dissolved,
then you've got a
problem. אמרה ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי מנא ידעינן? Amlei
Rav Aha brei de Rava l'Rav Ashi minay yadin? How do you
know if the inside has dissolved, so how do you know whether
the branches have remained or not, or maybe they've dissolved? So אמר
ליה, amar lei, מייתינן צעדי דקוניא, maycinan tzo'ada d'kunya, you take a
vessel that's somehow, you know,
that's plated or whatever it's called, anyway, with lead, that's lead-lined, so
it's, you know, you'll see everything that you put into it, ושפכינן
לה בגווה, v'shafchinan lah b'gavah, and you empty out this lung that
the insides have liquefied into this vessel. אי איכא שריקי חיורי טרפה,
iy basey s'riki chivrey treifa, if it has white lines, טרפה, treifa,
then those white lines are these branches of the trachea and that
means that even the branches of the trachea have dissolved and then
it's a טרפה. treifa. ואי לא, v'ilo, and if
you see that they're not there,
well,
that's an interesting point. It means that they've dissolved. If they haven't
dissolved then they're still part of I guess the original structure, but
if they've actually see that they're part of the liquid that pours
out, then some of them have dissolved. That seems to be the
point. ואי לא כשרה, v'ilo k'sheira, but if you don't see any
of those white lines then they remain part of the actual structure
and none of them have dissolved and it's kosher. Okay, so I
guess we will end here. So I
guess, Dov, I know you're on schedule but I know you're doing
שבת, Shabbos, so do you want me to read three more lines
to get to the two dots or you want to end? Stay
going. Okay. So אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, so רב נחמן
Rav Nachman says, ריאה
שנימוקה וקרום שלה קיים כשרה. rei'ah she'nimokah v'krum shelah kayam k'sheira. If
the outer shell of the lung is there but it's נימוקה. nimokah.
How is נימוקה nimokah different? So רש"י Rashi says it doesn't mean
fully dissolved, it means that it's somewhat like it's somewhat has turned
a little bit mushy or something like that. So some of it
has it's created some type of a cavity in you know where
there used between the between for the outer and inner skin apparently,
but it's not totally liquefied. So that's kosher. That seems obvious if
liquefied is okay. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly,
ריאה שנימוקה וקרום שלה קיים, rei'ah she'nimokah v'krum shelah kayam, if it
has somehow shriveled and the still shell is there, that's okay, אפילו
מחזקת רביעית כשרה, afilu machazekes revi'is k'sheira, even if it created a
cavity that could contain a רביעית revi'is like three ounces, that's okay,
again because there's no hole even though some of it has dissolved
or shriveled. נטלה שלפוחית, nitla shalpushis, now we're going to do something
totally unrelated but it was taught at the same time, if the
womb is missing, שלה כשרה, shela k'sheira, that's kosher, okay an animal
without a womb. התליעה כבד שלה, hitli'ah kaveid shelah, let's say the
liver has become wormy. So we know that a missing liver as
long as a little bit or כזית kazayis is left is okay,
but let's say a diseased liver if it's wormy, so זה היה
מעשה, zeh hayah ma'aseh, this was a story, ועלו
עליה בני אסיא ג' רגלים ליבנה, v'alu aleha bnei asya gimel regalim
l'yavneh, and the people of אסיא, Asya, I guess Asia Minor, came
to יבנה Yavneh over three רגלים regalim to ask this question. One
wonders what's been happening to the meat during that time. Anyway, לרגל
שלישי התירו להם, l'regel shelishi hitiru lahem, by the third רגל regel
by the third רגל regel they finally come to a conclusion and
said that even a wormy liver is okay.
How would that be okay? That sounds really bad.
I know, what can I tell you? Well, a liver that's almost
completely missing is okay. By the way, I will point out that
תוספות Tosafot points out you know that there are a number of
organs that are not mentioned in this whole list and we don't
know what the story is, like this is the first time we're
hearing about the womb. So if you look at this תוספות Tosafot
he says, שלפוחית היינו במקום שהולד מונח, shalpushis hayno b'makom she'havlad munach,
אבל ניקב כיס השתן, aval nekaiv kis hashashen, what if it's the
urethra that has a hole in it, או ניטל טרפה, o nital
treifa, ומה שלא הוזכר לא במשנה ולא בגמרא, u'mash'hu hushkar lo bamishna
v'lo bagemara, שלא היה בכלל דקין, shelo hayah bechol nikhla dakim, maybe
it's included in small intestine, although last I checked the urethra wasn't
included in the small intestine. So that does point to the fact
that again a lot of organs aren't mentioned, this is the first
that we're hearing about the womb. Okay, so we will end here
and I leave you in the good hands of דב Dov for
וישלח Vayishlach for שבת Shabbos and I will meet up with you
again on Sunday.
That's a good question though.